Guide to the Brooklyn College collection CBHM.0009
Center for Brooklyn History
Brooklyn College collection
1935-2012
Center for Brooklyn History
CBHM.0009
3.2 Linear feet in 4 manuscript boxes, one flat box and one flat file folder
A collection of publications, ephemera and documents from Brooklyn College.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This is an artifical collection created in 2023 by combining Brooklyn College materials from other artifical collections: the Brooklyn schools collection (CBHM.0006), Brooklyn Historical Society ephemera collection (ARC.272), Brooklyn ephemera collection (BCMS.0007), and the Brooklyn Collection clipping files. Some of the materials were evidently sent to Brooklyn Public Library or the Brooklyn Historical Society at the time of their creation. The exact source of other materials is unknown.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series by type. Series 1: Documents and ephemera is arranged roughly chronologically. Series 2: Publications is arranged alphabetically by publication title.
Historical note
Founded in 1930, Brooklyn College was New York City's first public coeducational liberal arts college. The school was envisioned as a stepping stone for the children of immigrants and working-class people toward a better life through a free college education.
The first campus was in Downtown Brooklyn. Within two years, the college had spread to another building, and the idea of constructing a formal campus soon took hold. Several sites throughout the borough were considered, and the first president, William A. Boylan, embraced a large track in the Midwood neighborhood proposed by a young architect, Randolph Evans. Even before the site was chosen, Evans had drafted a design for a Georgian-style campus facing a central quadrangle and anchored by a library building with a tall tower. Conveniently, the land was owned by his employers and, at the time, was being used as a golf course, a football field, and the staging area for Barnum & Bailey Circus.
Despite the United States being in the throes of the Great Depression, progress was made quickly. On December 21, 1934, the city's Board of Estimate approved the purchase of the Midwood lot for $1,625,528. In January, the Public Works Administration of the federal government allocated $5 million for the buildings' construction. And on October 2, 1935, Mayor Fiorello La Guardia, in the presence of Boylan and Borough President Raymond V. Ingersoll, took a silver-plated shovel and symbolically broke ground for the official beginning of Brooklyn College's new campus. Workers enlisted in the Works Progress Administration (WPA) completed most of the buildings and landscaping within two years.
The college's reputation grew throughout the following decades, driven in part by a prominent faculty across the disciplines. Students were expected to be among the city's best as well, and were required to pass a stringent entrance exam and keep up with the rigorous course work.
In 1961, Brooklyn College became a member of the City University of New York just as the college was entering one of its most tumultuous periods. The Vietnam War, combined with the demands of emerging ethnic and racial empowerment movements, led to almost weekly protests. Both the student body and the faculty engaged in vigorous debates on and off campus, while the college became known for hosting controversial figures, including Abbie Hoffman and Bob Dylan.
In 1970 CUNY instituted an open-admissions policy that granted any New York City resident, regardless of academic credentials or ability, the right to attend a CUNY school. As a result, enrollment at Brooklyn College swelled to more than 30,000 students in only a few years. This led to severe overcrowding in classrooms, depletion of services and budget concerns that resulted in an acute fiscal emergency in 1975. The college closed its downtown campus and began "retrenchment," cutting back tenured faculty, administration and many services.
In 1981 the college created a nationally recognized Core Curriculum designed to give students a strong foundation in the liberal arts. In addition to strengthening the curriculum, the college began to hire new faculty again.
The improvement of the curriculum was mirrored by an increased effort to improve facilities. A renovation and expansion of the library began in the late 1990s. The West Quad Center — the first new building to be added to the campus in decades — followed. Next came the Leonard & Claire Tow Center for the Performing Arts. The most recent project is the Roosevelt Science Teaching Commons. The complex will be dedicated to promoting an increased public understanding of science and to engaging the community.
The college's ninth president, Karen L. Gould, created four new schools in Fall 2011. The existing School of Education was joined by the School of Business, the School of Humanities and Social Sciences, the School of Natural and Behavioral Sciences, and the School of Visual, Media and Performing Arts.
Source
"Our History." https://www.brooklyn.edu/about/history/ Accessed July 24, 2023.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Brooklyn schools collection (CBHM.0006)
Brooklyn yearbook collection (BCMS.0031)
Records of the Brooklyn Council for Social Planning (BCMS.0039)
Schlagel and Wolf family papers (2013.008)
Arnie Goldwag Brooklyn Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) collection (ARC.002)
Caltagirone family photographs (ARC.305)
Donald L. Nowlan Brooklyn collection (ARC.120)
Photographs from the Brooklyn Daily Eagle (BCMS.0002)
Books at CBH
Parisi, Barbara. The history of Brooklyn's three major performing arts institutions: the Brooklyn Academy of Music, Brooklyn Center for the Performing Arts at Brooklyn College, St. Ann's Center for Restoration and the Arts, Inc. Ann Arbor, MI: University Microfilms International, 1991. 790.068 P
Watson, Gladys Hipple. The Brooklyn College student; a pilgrim's progress. New York: Twayne Publishers, 1966. 378.7471 B872 W
Horowitz, Murray M. Brooklyn College, the first half-century. New York: Brooklyn College Press, 1981. 378.74723 H
Coulton, Thomas Evans. A city college in action: struggle and achievement at Brooklyn College, 1930-1955. New York: Harper, 1955. 378.73 C87 C8
Stern, Bernard Herbert. Adult experience and college degrees; a report of the experimental degree project for adults at Brooklyn College, 1954-58. Cleveland: Press of Western Reserve University, 1960. 378.13 S839 A
Goodhartz, Abraham Samuel (ed.) A commitment to youth: the Brooklyn College student personnel program. New York: Bookman Associates, 1960. 378.7471 G652 C
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the activities of Brooklyn College from 1935, the year ground was broken on its large Midwood campus, into the 2010s. There is no documentation in this collection of the college's early years in Downtown Brooklyn. The collection consists of publications, documents, and ephemera documenting student life, academics, and faculty and alumni activities. Of particular note are materials relating to campus life and especially student protest activity in the late 1960s and early 1970s.
College students -- New York (State) -- Kings County; College teachers -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Student life and customs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Student newspapers and periodicals; Student publications -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Education, Higher -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Protest and social movements
- Series 1: Documents and ephemera
  - Catalogs and pamphlets, 1935-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Commencement programs, 1938-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Library materials, 1948-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Event programs and flyers, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Presidential statements and addresses, 1955-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1958-1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Conferences and symposiums, 1960-1977, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 9, Box 5)
  - Ephemera, circa 1960s-1970s, circa 2000s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Community Children's Theatre, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Press packets, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Performing Arts and Conservatory of Music, 1968-1992 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes Afro-American Theatre workshop and Opera Theatre materials.
  - Press releases, 1968-1970s, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Student protest activity, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Brooklyn College Fund/Foundation, 1971, 1988, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Adult Education Program, 1974-1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Museum of the Borough of Brooklyn, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 6, Folder Flat File)
  - Alumni materials, 1982-1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Weekend College, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Brooklyn College Academy, 1989-circa 2000s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Brooklyn College Community Partnership (BCCP), 2008-2010 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Sub-series 1.1: Brooklyn Center for the Performing Arts at Brooklyn College (BCBC)
    - Flyers and mailings, 1970-2003 (Box 3, Folder 1, Folder Flat File)
    - Programs, 1983-1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - News releases, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series 2: Publications
  - American Poet, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - BCAA [Brooklyn College Alumni Association] Bulletin, 1955, 1975-1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - BC Today, 1981 (Box 5)
  - Brooklyn College Magazine, 1985-2012 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Brooklyn College News, 1980-1983 (Box 5)
  - Brooklyn College Today, 1966-1968, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 7, Box 5)
  - Bulletin, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - CUNY Community Newsletter, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Faculty/Staff Bulletin, 1970-1980 (Box 3, Folder 10, Box 5)
  - Ken, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - Kingsman, 1962-1972 (Box 5)
  - The Library Associate newsletter, 1966-1975 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Night Call, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Nocturne, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Observer Kaleidoscope, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - The Ol' Spigot, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
    "The official newspaper of student government."
  - President's report, 1955-1957, 1992-1998 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Summer Session News, 1971, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Vistas, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 6)